Mount Sinai Hospital Collection 0009.002.005
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
Mount Sinai Hospital
1922-2012
0009.002.005
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
2.0 Cubic feet 2 cubic feet plus 2 oversize scrapbooks
In Hartford, as elsewhere in the early part of the 20th Century, Jewish physicians were barred from practicing at most hospitals. This wide spread "gentleman's agreement" kept Jewish doctors out of the network of referrals, and forced them to put their patients on admittance waiting lists until a gentile colleague could take over. This situation created substantial financial hardships for the physicians. Once admitted to Gentile-run hospitals Jewish patients faced language barriers and lack of access to kosher food. Moreover, the wide spread discrimination in the medical profession meant that Jewish interns had difficulty obtaining training. To correct this situation locally, a group of concerned physicians and citizens established an association in 1918 called "The Abraham Jacobi Hospital." Although an option to purchase land for the hospital was obtained from the Keney Estate at the corner of Love Lane and Westland Street, the war delayed progress on the hospital for several years. In 1922, the association changed its name to Mt. Sinai Hospital and purchased the Morgan Brainard mansion at 119 Capitol Avenue. The first hospital facility opened in 1923 with 75 beds. Another problem faced by Jews was the difficulty of getting nurses to visit Jewish patients. In 1925, Mt. Sinai opened a nursing school to address this need. The school closed in 1936. In 1940, Mt. Sinai was able to obtain the former Hebrew Home for Children building on Blue Hills Avenue. It began a campaign to remodel and expand the site, but progress was again delayed by war until 1950. By the mid-1960s, Jewish residents were leaving the North End of Hartford in large numbers and moving to West Hartford and Bloomfield. Most other Jewish institutions followed their constituents, but Mt. Sinai continued to commit itself to its neighborhood and it expanded. This choice, though beneficial for the Hartford community as a whole, was nearly disastrous for the hospital. As the income-per-capita of the surrounding area declined, the percentage of Mt. Sinai's unreimbursed medical care rose dramatically. Though Hartford Hospital and St. Francis Hospital contributed funds to cut the shortfall, Mt. Sinai's financial problems grew more and more severe each year. In the late 1980s, Mt. Sinai started exploring opportunities to merge with another hospital. Mt. Sinai and St. Francis affiliated in 1990 and formally merged, under the name of St. Francis, in 1995. The great strength of the Mt. Sinai collection is the compilation of key documents made by Dr. Isidore S. Geetter for the 50th anniversary of the hospital. These include minutes for the early establishment of Abraham Jacobi Hospital and Mt. Sinai Hospital. Dr. Geetter also preserved annual reports and staff memos from the 1940s, 50s, and 60s that provide a continuous narrative during its major growth and decline cycle. Though compact, this collection offers a substantial amount of vital historical data.
Abraham Jacobi Hospital; Annual Reports; Blue Hills Avenue, Hartford, CT; Board of Directors; Buildings, Hartford; Education; Kashrut Commission of Greater Hartford; Mount Sinai Hospital; Newsletters; Nursing; Women's Auxiliary
- Series I: AB- AN
  - Abraham Jacobi Hospital/Board of Directors/Members, 1922-2009 (Box 1)
  - Abraham Jacobi Hospital/Board of Directors/Minutes 3/1918 to 6/1922, 1922-2009 (Box 1)
  - Abraham Jacobi Hospital/Correspondence, 1922-2009 (Box 1)
  - Abraham Jacobi Hospital/Historical Highlights, 1922-2009 (Box 1)
  - Abraham Jacobi Hospital/Incorporation, 1922-2009 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1920s and 1930s, 1922-2009 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1940s, 1922-2009 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1950s, 1922-2009 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1960-1965, 1922-2009 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1966-1969, 1922-2009 (Box 1)
- Series II: AU-B
  - Auxiliary/Anniversaries, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Auxiliary/Annual Reports, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Auxiliary/Constitution and By-Laws, Men's Auxiliary, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Auxiliary/Constitution and By-Laws, Women's Auxiliary, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Auxiliary/Education Programs, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Auxiliary/Fundraising, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Auxiliary/Historical Highlights, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Auxiliary/Junior League, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Auxiliary/Meeting Programs, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Auxiliary/Minutes, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Auxiliary/Miscellaneous, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Auxiliary/Newsletters, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Auxiliary/Officers and Members, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Auxiliary/Scrapbooks, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Auxiliary/Volunteer Activities, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Awards and Honors Received, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors/Members, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors/Members 1954, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors/Minutes 6/1922 to 3/1923, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors/ Minutes 1/1962 to 4/1962, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Buildings/500 Blue Hills Avenue/1940, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Buildings/500 Blue Hills Avenue/1950 new facility, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Buildings/500 Blue Hills Avenue/1959? expansion, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Buildings/500 Blue Hills Avenue/1972 expansion, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Buildings/119 Capitol Avenue, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Buildings/119 Capitol Avenue/Campaign 1923, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Buildings/119 Capitol Avenue/Deeds 1922, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Buildings/119 Capitol Avenue/Expansion 1939, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
  - Buildings/1 Northwestern Drive/1987, 1922-2009 (Box 2)
- Series III: C-K
  - Charitable Activities, 1922-2009 (Box 3)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1922-2009 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1922-2009 (Box 3)
  - Education Programs, 1922-2009 (Box 3)
  - Education Programs/ Dr.Geeter/In-Service Education Program., 1922-2009 (Box 3)
  - Fundraising (other than building campaigns), 1922-2009 (Box 3)
  - Historical Highlights, 1922-2009 (Box 3)
  - Historical Highlights/Geeter, Dr. I. S. - "Historical Development of Hospitals under Jewish Auspices", 1922-2009 (Box 3)
  - Historical Highlights/Geeter, Dr. I. S. - "To Make a Hospital: 1916-1973" draft, with cover letter to Richard Koopman, 1922-2009 (Box 3)
  - Historical Highlights/Lazarus, Barry A. - "The Practice of Medicine and Prejudice in a New England Town" Incorporation, 1922-2009 (Box 3)
  - Investments, 1922-2009 (Box 3)
  - Kashrut, 1922-2009 (Box 3)
- Series IV: M-Z
  - Membership, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Merger, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters/Employee Memos 1951-1952, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters/Employee Memos 1953-1954, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters/Employee Memos 1955-1969, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters/For Staff Members, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters/For the Public (including the Mt. Sinai Bulletin and Life in the Mount Sinai Hospital, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Nursing School, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Programs/JHSGH April 26, 2009/ Leon Chameides presentation on Mount Sinai (includes PowerPoint on CD), 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Radiologic Technology School, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Reporter (the newspaper of the hospital, vol. 1, number 1), 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Special Medical Programs, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Staff Members+, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Tovia Ann Baby Club for children delivered at the hospital, includes items from Kramer family, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Auxiliary and Volunteers, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Blue Hills Avenue Facility, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Capitol Avenue Facility, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Nursing Classes, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
  - Women's Auxiliary Luncheon 1977, located in oversized draw #1, 1922-2009 (Box 4)
- Series V: Artifacts
  - Women's Auxiliary lapel pin, 1922-2009
- Scrapbooks (Oversize 1)